Finding Aid for Chief Marshal (University of Michigan) records, 1914-[ongoing]
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Chief Marshal (University of Michigan) records 1914-[ongoing]
University of Michigan. Chief Marshal.
8753 Bimu E3 2
The Chief Marshal of the University is the individual responsible for planning and participating in both official and ceremonial University events, including commencement ceremonies. The position began around 1883 and is usually filled by a member of the University faculty. The Chief Marshal records primarily include correspondence, floor plans, commencement programs, and planning materials related to university commencement exercises from 1914 to the present.
13 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were transferred from the Chief Marshal (Donor No. 5384 ) in October, 1981, with periodic updates.
The collection is open to research.
While the Chief Marshal's main tasks revolve around planning commencement ceremonies at the University of Michigan, he is also a key figure and "trouble shooter" in many official and ceremonial university events besides commencement. The role of Chief Marshal has most frequently been filled by a member of the University faculty. The current Chief Marshal was appointed by the Provost and works with the University Office of Development and Events.
The earliest known Chief Marshal, originally called the "Grand Marshal," was Major Harrison Soule in 1883. Soule was the Treasurer of the University, and a Civil War veteran. His military bearing and impressive uniform while leading the faculty and graduates during the commencement ceremonies evidently set a high precedent for the Chief Marshal position. Although the Chief Marshal led the procession it seems that, at first, any changes in the commencement ceremony had to be approved by the current President of the University before they could be implemented. By 1931 the Chief Marshal responsibilities included much greater participation in orchestrating the time schedules and managing the many details involved with planning commencement ceremonies. Some of those responsibilities were shared with the Assistant Secretary of the University. As the University of Michigan has grown in size, so have the commencement ceremonies grown in complexity. The Chief Marshal Records reveal the diverse aspects of conducting large commencements, from planning for bad weather to determining the seating arrangements and ordering of the hundreds of graduates.
The names and approximate dates of service of the Chief Marshals of the University of Michigan are as follows:
1883-1908 Major Harrison Soule
1908-1915 Dean Mortimer E. Cooley
1916-1943 Professor Louis M. Gram
1944-1962 Glenn Leslie Alt
1963-1970 John E. Milholland
1971-1986 Robert Blynn Harris
1987-1991 William Maloney
1992-1999 Dale E. Briggs
2000- 2007 Linda K. Gregerson
2008-2013 Mika LaVaque-Manty
Records of the Chief Marshal of the University include correspondence, floor plans, programs, and planning materials related to University commencement exercises. Since all of the papers have been filed chronologically by commencement date, they form only one series entitled, Commencement Papers, spanning the years 1914-present. This collection is ongoing and more accessions may be expected.
Since 2001 commencement ceremonies have been recorded. They exist as VHS cassettes and more recently as DVDs.
Subjects:
University of Michigan--Commencements.; University of Michigan. Chief Marshall.
- Commencement Papers 1914-[ongoing]
  - 1914-1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1949 (Box 2)
  - 1950-1957 (Box 3)
  - 1958-1962 (Box 4)
  - 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - 1968-1973 (Box 7)
  - Robben Fleming Inauguration 1968 (Box 7)
  - 1974-1981 (Box 8)
  - 1982-1990 (Box 9)
  - Statistics Re: Attendance at Commencements (Box 9)
  - College of Engineering Commencements and Convocations (Box 9)
  - 1991-2000 (Box 10)
  - 2001-2009 (Box 11)
  - 2010- (Box 13)
- Video Recordings of Commencement Ceremonies
  - VHS videotapes
    - 1996 Spring (Box 12)
    - 1997 Spring (Box 12)
    - 1998 Winter (Box 12)
    - 1999 Spring (Box 12)
    - 1999 Winter (Box 12)
    - 2000 Winter (Box 12)
    - 2001 Spring (Box 12)
    - 2001 Winter (Box 12)
    - 2001 Winter, Graduate Degrees (Box 12)
    - 2002 Spring (Box 12)
    - 2002 Winter (Box 12)
    - 2003 Spring (Box 12)
    - 2003 Winter (Box 12)
    - 2004 Spring (Box 12)
    - 2004 Winter (Box 12)
  - DVDs
    - 2004 Winter (Box 12)
    - 2005 Spring (Box 12)
    - 2006 Spring (Box 12)
  - DVCam
    - 2005 Spring (Box 12)
Related Materials
Researchers interested in the Chief Marshal Records may also wish to consult the commencement files in the Bentley Historical Library vertical file (call number: Fimu E3), especially "Notes on the Commencement Procession" by Joseph C. Wagner, December 15, 1936, which describes the work of the first Chief Marshals. There is also a relevant article on the responsibilities of the Chief Marshal entitled, "Conning the Campus," in the Michigan Alumnus Volume 37 No. 33, June 27, 1931, pg. 647.
The University of Michigan Vertical File also contains files on individual classes (Class of [year], call number Fimu F99). these files contain additional commencement material.